Guide to the NYU Abu Dhabi Capstone Archives AD.MC.004
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
- Science Division Projects, 2014-2019
  - Physics
    - Hattori, Soichiro. Detecting Potential Jupiter-Analog Exoplanets In The Archival Kepler Dataset., 2016; 2016-0046; While exoplanet research has made rapid progress in recent years, there is a shortage of research in detecting long orbital period exoplanets. Just as our Solar System's evolution
      While exoplanet research has made rapid progress in recent years, there is a shortage of research in detecting long orbital period exoplanets. Just as our Solar System's evolution was affected by the presence of a large long orbital period planet, Jupiter, these exoplanets may therefore serve as an indicator of a complex planetary system like our own. Using the archival Kepler data, a publically available dataset generated by the NASA Kepler space observatory, we conduct a search for potential novel Jupiter-Analog exoplanets. A modified and simplified box model, a line segment model, was used to search through the entire 1TB dataset in 4 days. The algorithm returned 672 stars out of 206,111 stars in the entire dataset. While there were more than 600 false positives, 18 stars have potentially new transit events. We propose that follow-up observations are made on these 18 stars to confirm or deny potential exoplanets.
    - Magnusson, Allen. Amelioration of an X-ray Fluorescence Scanning Spectrometer for Applications to Cultural Heritage Studies., 2016; 2016-0027; X-Ray Fluorescence is a powerful nuclear technique for analyzing elemental composition and is well suited for non-destructive, in situ investigations of art and artifacts. The technique offers interdisciplinary applications and can be used alone or as complementary to other techniques such as Raman spectroscopy. In collaboration with the LABEC laboratory in Florence, Italy, we have modified an existing XRF scanning spectrometer by integrating a laser telemetry sensor into the system hardware and software. Positional feedback from the sensor was used to automatically regulate scanner-to-specimen distance during an areal scan. With this regulation in place, X-ray elemental distribution scans were able to be performed for a widened range of non-planar sample geometries without sacrificing data quality or posing risks to analyzed specimens. Dedicated tests at LABEC, the Opificio Delle Pietre Dure, and in Abu Dhabi have confirmed the upgraded versatility of the XRF system in analyzing a range of Cultural Heritage specimens. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0027)
      X-Ray Fluorescence is a powerful nuclear technique for analyzing elemental composition and is well suited for non-destructive, in situ investigations of art and artifacts. The technique offers interdisciplinary applications and can be used alone or as complementary to other techniques such as Raman spectroscopy. In collaboration with the LABEC laboratory in Florence, Italy, we have modified an existing XRF scanning spectrometer by integrating a laser telemetry sensor into the system hardware and software. Positional feedback from the sensor was used to automatically regulate scanner-to-specimen distance during an areal scan. With this regulation in place, X-ray elemental distribution scans were able to be performed for a widened range of non-planar sample geometries without sacrificing data quality or posing risks to analyzed specimens. Dedicated tests at LABEC, the Opificio Delle Pietre Dure, and in Abu Dhabi have confirmed the upgraded versatility of the XRF system in analyzing a range of Cultural Heritage specimens.
    - Pazos Clemens, Luis. Charecterization of Multi Pixel Photon Counters for particle detection purposes., 2016; 2016-0040; A comprehensive characterization of novel Multi Pixel Photon Counters (MPPCs) was performed to assess their potential as a substitute for the type of light detectors, photomultiplier tubes (PMTs), currently used for applications such as liquid noble gas particle detectors and gamma ray spectroscopy. The study was focused on their response to light with wavelengths in the vacuum ultraviolet range like that obtained from the liquid xenon and argon scintillation utilized in particle detectors. In order to recreate the conditions of said detectors part of the study was realized under cryogenic conditions. The wide yet precise range of wavelengths used was obtained by using a state-of-the-art monochromator. To further evaluate the performance of the MPPCs they were used in the analysis of scintillation light emitted by LYSO crystals and its response to temperature changes. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0040)
      A comprehensive characterization of novel Multi Pixel Photon Counters (MPPCs) was performed to assess their potential as a substitute for the type of light detectors, photomultiplier tubes (PMTs), currently used for applications such as liquid noble gas particle detectors and gamma ray spectroscopy. The study was focused on their response to light with wavelengths in the vacuum ultraviolet range like that obtained from the liquid xenon and argon scintillation utilized in particle detectors. In order to recreate the conditions of said detectors part of the study was realized under cryogenic conditions. The wide yet precise range of wavelengths used was obtained by using a state-of-the-art monochromator. To further evaluate the performance of the MPPCs they were used in the analysis of scintillation light emitted by LYSO crystals and its response to temperature changes.
    - Shaff, Dean. Cleaning XENON100 Waveforms With Supervised MAchine Learning Algorithms., 2016; 2016-0030; We use two supervised machine learning techniques, multilayer perceptron and boosted decision tree, to increase signal efficiency in data from the XENON100 dark matter experiment. Existing techniques for distinguishing between signal and background involve making threshold cuts on a quantity called entropy. Throughout the life of XENON100, this approach has become less efficient, particularly for run 12. Instead of using events as my basic data analysis unit, we use individual waveforms. After characterizing these waveforms in terms of high and low level variables, we train a Theano implementation of MLP and the TMVA implementation of BDT. Out physically well motivated choice of training data significantly outperformed a control training dataset, for both methods. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0030)
      We use two supervised machine learning techniques, multilayer perceptron and boosted decision tree, to increase signal efficiency in data from the XENON100 dark matter experiment. Existing techniques for distinguishing between signal and background involve making threshold cuts on a quantity called entropy. Throughout the life of XENON100, this approach has become less efficient, particularly for run 12. Instead of using events as my basic data analysis unit, we use individual waveforms. After characterizing these waveforms in terms of high and low level variables, we train a Theano implementation of MLP and the TMVA implementation of BDT. Out physically well motivated choice of training data significantly outperformed a control training dataset, for both methods.
    - Al Qasim, Ahlam. Cubesat Raad for the Study of Terrestrial Gamma-Ray Flashes, 2017; 2017-0023; Terrestrial Gamma-Ray Flashes (TGFs) are sudden bursts of gamma ray radiation triggered by lightning or thunderstorms and are channeled above the Earth's atmosphere and into outer space, and thus cannot be detected from Earth. The current leading model that is used to explain the mechanism behind TGF production is Relativistic Runaway Electron Avalanche (RREA) phenomenon, but this model is being challenged by some of the most recent key TGF observations, including AGILE and FERMI observations, which suggests that this may not be the best model to explain TGF emission. CubeSat Raad is a proposal for a study to identify a useful experiment for TGF Science, which can be miniaturized and eventually integrated on a cubesat. The instrumentation proposed for the purpose of the experiment is a 3U cubesat and a gamma-ray detector in the $\mathrm{10 keV - 1000 keV}$ range. The goal is to explicitly target events connected to low energy gamma rays emitted from the earth's atmosphere and in turn collect and analyze data focused and specific on this phenomenon to improve correlation studies with lightning and other atmospheric parameters. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2017-0023)
      Terrestrial Gamma-Ray Flashes (TGFs) are sudden bursts of gamma ray radiation triggered by lightning or thunderstorms and are channeled above the Earth's atmosphere and into outer space, and thus cannot be detected from Earth. The current leading model that is used to explain the mechanism behind TGF production is Relativistic Runaway Electron Avalanche (RREA) phenomenon, but this model is being challenged by some of the most recent key TGF observations, including AGILE and FERMI observations, which suggests that this may not be the best model to explain TGF emission. CubeSat Raad is a proposal for a study to identify a useful experiment for TGF Science, which can be miniaturized and eventually integrated on a cubesat. The instrumentation proposed for the purpose of the experiment is a 3U cubesat and a gamma-ray detector in the $\mathrm{10 keV - 1000 keV}$ range. The goal is to explicitly target events connected to low energy gamma rays emitted from the earth's atmosphere and in turn collect and analyze data focused and specific on this phenomenon to improve correlation studies with lightning and other atmospheric parameters.
    - Isakovic, Jasmina. Electromagnetic fields around neurons interact with T-cells in the CNS and initiate autoimmune response: a parallel between multiple sclerosis and ischemic stroke., 2017; 2017-0029; Multiple sclerosis (MS) is an autoimmune disease where a mutation in the gene encoding for a protein belonging to the NLR Family Pyrin Domain Containing 12 (NLRP12) enables the T-cells to penetrate the blood-brain barrier and damage the myelin sheath. Expanding upon Dr. Bjorn Nordenstrom's "Biologically Closed Electrical Circuits", this paper utilizes computational electrodynamics in Matlab and an in vivo MRI cell tracking study to hypothesize that negative charge on the surface of the T-cell gets attracted to the electromagnetic fields generated around the nodes of Ranvier and initiates the autoimmune response. By manipulating the electromagnetic forces of attraction between the cells, the MRI study showed that T-cell's mobility was impaired post-glucocorticoid receptor antagonization. The electrodynamic modeling determined the spatial and temporal progression of the electromagnetic field to quantify the nature of its interaction with the T-cell's surface charge and its role within the context of MS etiology. The potential implications of this research could lead to better understanding of the disease's symptoms and provide a framework to explain its uncertain times of onset. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2017-0029)
      Multiple sclerosis (MS) is an autoimmune disease where a mutation in the gene encoding for a protein belonging to the NLR Family Pyrin Domain Containing 12 (NLRP12) enables the T-cells to penetrate the blood-brain barrier and damage the myelin sheath. Expanding upon Dr. Bjorn Nordenstrom's "Biologically Closed Electrical Circuits", this paper utilizes computational electrodynamics in Matlab and an in vivo MRI cell tracking study to hypothesize that negative charge on the surface of the T-cell gets attracted to the electromagnetic fields generated around the nodes of Ranvier and initiates the autoimmune response. By manipulating the electromagnetic forces of attraction between the cells, the MRI study showed that T-cell's mobility was impaired post-glucocorticoid receptor antagonization. The electrodynamic modeling determined the spatial and temporal progression of the electromagnetic field to quantify the nature of its interaction with the T-cell's surface charge and its role within the context of MS etiology. The potential implications of this research could lead to better understanding of the disease's symptoms and provide a framework to explain its uncertain times of onset.
    - Zheng, Tiantian. Monte Carlo simulations of intracellular transport by teams of kinesin-1 molecular motors, 2017; 2017-0038; We develop a new computational model of cargo transport by multiple kinesin-1 motors which incorporates recent findings involving the asymmetric force-run length relations of single kinesin. By analyzing trajectories simulated with an assisting force applied to the cargo, we find that the velocity of the cargo is solely determined by the dynamics of the leading and lagging motors of the team hauling the cargo. This ``two-motor model" reduces to a one-motor model under high assisting forces, allowing the development of an analytical expression that captures cargo dynamics under these conditions. This expression incorporates the single motor properties and therefore allows us to extract these properties by fitting the cargo velocity response to force. This provides a powerful framework for measuring individual motor properties in vivo where cargo are typically hauled by teams of motors. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2017-0038)
      We develop a new computational model of cargo transport by multiple kinesin-1 motors which incorporates recent findings involving the asymmetric force-run length relations of single kinesin. By analyzing trajectories simulated with an assisting force applied to the cargo, we find that the velocity of the cargo is solely determined by the dynamics of the leading and lagging motors of the team hauling the cargo. This ``two-motor model" reduces to a one-motor model under high assisting forces, allowing the development of an analytical expression that captures cargo dynamics under these conditions. This expression incorporates the single motor properties and therefore allows us to extract these properties by fitting the cargo velocity response to force. This provides a powerful framework for measuring individual motor properties in vivo where cargo are typically hauled by teams of motors.
    - AlKhouri, Fatema. Optimizing Trigger Parameters for the Detection of Terrestrial Gamma-Ray Flashes, 2018; 2018-0084 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0084)
      In this paper, a description of Terrestrial Gamma-Ray Flash (TGF) simulation method will be provided as well its usage for determining mission parameters and trigger criteria. A database of 1000 TGFs at different radial distances (up to 1k km) was created for 4 different configurations of CeBr3-crystal, γ-ray detectors. The expected TGF count rate within 1000 km was determined to be roughly 1.64 per day, with mostly very few to no counts observed. The expected background was also simulated; the external background was derived from the background accumulations of the Fermi satellite, and the intrinsic background determined in the laboratory. The total background count rates were as follows: 9.600, 38.399, 86.399, and 172.797 counts/second for the 1, 4, 9, and 18 crystal arrays respectively. The simulations were tested for optimum trigger criteria- such as energy thresholds, trigger window sizes, and count rates per trigger window.
    - AlMannaei, Aisha. RAAD CubeSat Mission for The Study of Terrestrial Gamma-ray Flashes: Space Qualification Document, 2018; 2018-0090 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0090)
      Terrestrial Gamma-Ray Flashes (TGFs) are sudden bursts of gamma rays that occur in the Earth's atmosphere and escape into outer space which are triggered by lightning or thunderstorm activity. Previous detectors used to study TGFs were limited by their slow response times and therefore more observations are needed to construct a model to describe this phenomena. The proposed detector is based on Cerium(III) Bromide crystals coupled to a compact (Hamamatsu R11265U-100) photomultiplier tube. This instrument will have a faster time response, high resolution (3.5% at 661 keV) and a high density. Given the limited power consumption on a Cubesat (2-6W), the aim is to develop a low cost detector with extremely low power requirements and a response time of less than 100 ns that can be standardized to fit within 1U of a CubeSat. This describes the characteristics of the prototype unit detector such as linearity, voltage gain, and the gain as a function of temperature for the crystal and PMT.
    - D'Alterio, Kristopher. Automatization of Faint NEO Follow-Up, 2018; 2018-0050 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0050)
      In this paper we describe a method to improve the follow up process for near earth objects (NEOs), especially for faint and fast moving NEOs. Current follow up procedures typically use imaging with telescope in sidereal rotation and as a consequence the image of the moving NEO is a linear track instead of a point source. This makes it difficult to recover faint or fast moving sources. We propose a new follow up method where the telescope tracks the NEO rather than tracking with sidereal motion, and therefore focuses the image onto a smaller number of pixels. In order to explore the effectiveness of such a method, we have created simulated images which accurately depict the images that would be found if this method were applied, and determined the recovery rate of NEOs for such simulated images under varying conditions. We have also identified future work that should be done in order to improve these recovery rates, and laid out a framework for making a complete statistical evaluation of the method, which would give a description of the recovery rate of the method as a function of the magnitude and velocity of an NEO.
    - Stoychev, Boyan. Constraining nature of dark matter with high redshift galaxies, 2018; 2018-0056 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0056)
      Warm Dark Matter (WDM) models provide a promising alternative cosmological scenario to the standard Λ Cold Dark Matter (CDM) model. Numerous studies have employed cosmological numerical simulations to constrain the allowed mass of WDM particles based on low-redshift observational data. When restricted to this range, viable WDM models produce indistinguishable predictions at low redshift that are in agreement with CDM. In this work, galaxy formation at z = 6-10 was studied in the framework of the NIHAO project, comparing 3keV WDM to CDM. Halo mass functions were calculated from dark-matter-only simulations of the CDM and WDM scenarios, and fitted using Markov Chain Monte Carlo. Simulations of galaxy formation using hydrodynamics were used to construct stellar mass - halo mass relations, which were then fitted with power laws. Those simulations were also used to calculate the fraction of galaxies that do not form stars as a function of halo mass. Finally, the above calculations were used to construct stellar mass functions for the two models at redshift 6-10, with the hope that the James Webb Space Telescope may be able to discriminate between the two models after its launch in 2020.
    - Torres, Rodrigo. Deployment of a Multidetector X-ray Fluorescence Spectrometer, 2018; 2018-0059 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0059)
      We present a multidetector X-ray fluorescence spectrometer, developed in collaboration with the Laboratory for Cultural Heritage (LABEC) in Florence. Principally, the mechanics and the software of the instrument were modified so as to allow the incorporation of an additional detec- tor. Additionally, through the optimization of the digital pulse processor acquisition and shaping parameters, an improvement to the energy resolution of a factor of two was attained. Further debugging, customization, and optimization allowed for the improvement on the acquisition times by a factor of ∼100, and the instrument's portability. Finally, we reflect shortly on the ongoing work during this current stage of instrumental development and on the future applications of this X-ray fluorescence spectrometer to cultural heritage research projects at NYUAD.
    - Udrescu, Silviu. The Effect of Radiative Feedback on Galaxy Structure, 2018; 2018-0098 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0098)
      Simulations of galaxy formations rely on different feedback mechanisms in order to reproduce the observed galaxy baryonic scaling relations and morphology. Although the explosive feedback can reproduce many of the observed properties of the galaxies, such as the stellar mass-halo mass relationship, it creates disks that are too thick. In this paper we present a study of the effects of the radiative feedback on gas cooling inside the simulations and its effects on the galaxy structure. This includes the ionizing radiation coming from young and old stars. In addition, a new model for the UV background radiation, represented by the radiation coming from other galaxies or active galactic nuclei, has been implemented, which proved to have a lower feedback effect compared to the old NIHAO implementation. The star formation rate is reduced after the introduction of the new local photoionization effect, due to an increase in the cooling time of the gas. However, due to the above-mentioned effect of the new UV background, most of the properties of the newly simulated galaxies have attained values similar to the ones in the old simulations. The thickness of the disk was not significantly affected.
    - Sinha, Vamika. Nature versus Nurture: Star Formation Rates in NIHAO, 2019; 2019-0103 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0103)
      I study the star formation rates of galaxies throughout their lifetimes using a large sample of hydrodynamical, cosmological simulations. I show that blackhole feedback is successful in quenching star formation in the largest galaxies. I construct a new quantity, Δ log Star Formation Rate, that relates the star formation rate of individual galaxies to galaxies similar to them in age and mass. I find an inverse correlation between halo formation time, measured through galaxy concentration, and Δ log SFR. Galaxies with halos that form earlier tend to underproduce stars throughout their lifetimes, while late bloomers tend to be chronic overproducers of stars. This is evidence that dark matter may play more of a role in driving star formation than previously realized.
    - Rosenthal, Michael. Mapping the Warped H2O Maser Disk in the Low-Mass Galaxy IC 750, 2019; 2019-0098 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0098)
      We present the first map of water masers in the active galactic nucleus (AGN) of the dwarf galaxy IC 750. Water masers at 22 GHz can penetrate the obscuring dust around Type 2 AGNs. Very Long Baseline Interferometry (VLBI) images of the central parsec of IC 750 reveal a nearly edge-on, warped disk of diameter ~0.22 pc x D / 13.8 Mpc. The disk lacks emission around the galaxy recession velocity of 701 km/s, so we fit Keplerian rotation curves for a 0.5 x 0.5 mas grid of possible dynamical centers. By accepting only centers for which the masses determined separately from each side of the disk agree within 5%, we determine a best-fit BH mass of 8.0 +0.8 / -0.4 solar masses. This mass constitutes the lowest-ever such measurement for a water maser system or obscured AGN.
    - Soliman, Nadine. Black Holes in NIHAO, 2019; 2019-0072 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0072)